A Guide to the Papers of J. Henry McCoy, 1918-1976
Special Collections, Perry Library, Old Dominion University
Special Collections, Perry Library, Old Dominion University
A Guide to the Papers of J. Henry McCoy 1918-1976
Special Collections, Perry Library, Old Dominion University
1-1B5
1 Hollinger document case
McCoy, J. Henry
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Open to researchers without restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift from J. Henry McCoy on March 16, 1978.
Biographical Information
Dr. J. Henry McCoy, Jr. attended Norfolk Division of William and Mary (now Old Dominion University) and graduated from Medical College of Virginia. In 1968, he was appointed to the Old Dominion University Board of Visitors. Later McCoy was appointed Vice-Chairman of the Local Board of Tidewater Community College. During the mid 1980's, Dr. McCoy represented the Kempsville Borough on the Virginia Beach City Council. He became Mayor of Virginia Beach in 1984. His term as Mayor ended in 1986.
Scope and Content
The papers of J. Henry McCoy date from 1918 to 1976. They document McCoy's professional life as a member of the ODU Board of Visitors and as Vice Chair of Tidewater Community College. This collection contains McCoy's correspondence with Old Dominion College / University and Tidewater Community College, the Commonwealth of Virginia, Virginia-Tidewater Dental Association, Alpha Kappa Psi, the US Congress, and Associated Naval Architects. Included also are generic/organization letters, proposals, job descriptions, program progress reports, meeting minutes, community college general information, and postcards that McCoy collected. McCoy's scrapbook materials include newspaper articles about McCoy's appointment to the Board of Visitors and letters of congratulations on the accomplishment; the hiring and resignation of James L. Bugg's Presidency of Old Dominion University; ODU students' concern over a racist hiring process and other general news about the University.
Index Terms
McCoy, J. Henry; Universities and colleges; Community colleges; Correspondence
Contents List
- Correspondence 29 June 1967-7 May 1976 (Box-folder 1:1)
  Contains correspondence with Old Dominion University including several letters related to the Division of Technology Dental Hygiene and Assisting Programs; The Alumni Association; Office of the President; The Mace and Crown; Student Caucus, School of Continuing Studies, and the Board of Visitors. Correspondence with the Commonwealth of Virginia: Governor's Office; Senate; and the House of Delegates. Correspondence also holds letters from Alpha Kappa Psi; The US Congress; and Associated Naval Architects.
- Correspondence 22 November 1970-25 June 1974 (Box-folder 1:2)
  Contains correspondence with Tidewater Community College and others from a variety of cities and companies in Virginia in relation to Tidewater Community College. Specifically: The Virginia Beach Sun; the Virginia Pilot; Virginia Department of Community Colleges; Virginia State Chamber of Commerce; Williams and Tazewell & Associates, Inc.; Dr. Robert J. Kirkman; House of Delegates; House of Representatives; Association of Community College Trustees; Virginia Beach City Public Schools; and Virginia Beach City Clerk.
- Old Dominion University Board of Visitors 6 November 1975-21 July 1976 (Box-folder 1:3)
  Includes generic letters addressed to the BOV members that discuss issues such as: how to select a new president using a search committee; search committee planning and candidates; and a profile of the University's future. Other documents include resumes and an analysis of the 1976 General Assembly.
- Meeting of the Executive Committee, ODU Board of Visitors 14 January 1976 (Box-folder 1:4)
  Contains papers revolving around the meetings of the Executive Committee beginning in January of 1976. These deal directly with the Executive Committee of the Board of Visitors. Discussed are topics related to dates of upcoming meetings; agenda; progress reports; presidency job description; draft letter to the Ambassador of Iran; Meeting minutes; and one letter to McCoy regarding a school of optometry.
- Old Dominion University and Intercollegiate Athletics (Box-folder 1:5)
  Provides a look into Intercollegiate athletics at Old Dominion University. These pieces illustrate the Four Year Plan for Intercollegiate Athletics developed by the Board of Visitors. This plan was devised in 1974 and devised in 1975. The memos in this series show correspondence between the Board of Visitors and Vice President for Student Affairs, and ODU President's Office. Also included is information about the Eastern College Athletic Conference.
- Virginia Community College System (Box-folder 1:6)
  Holds information about the Virginia Community College System. In general, the papers include information on policies, procedures, regulations and the curriculum offered by the system.
- Miscellaneous ("The Mission of the University", By-laws of the ODU Board of Visitors, In-state tuition application) (Box-folder 1:7)
  Contains one document of Old Dominion University's Mission Statement, Codes or Amendments of the Board of Visitors of Old Dominion, and one Domicile Application.
- Postcards from Camp Lee, Virginia 1918 (Box-folder 1:8)
  Contains photo-postcards. They include: The School of Arms, Knights of Columbus Hall, Old Dominion College Administration Building and Hughes Hall. There is also a postcard/souvenir folder of Camp Lee with photos of General Headquarters, Popular Place in Camp (Theatre), Officer's Club and its interior, Interior of Bakery, YWCA Hostess House, the Fire Department, Base Hospital, Red Cross Building, and photos of soldiers.
- Appointment to Board of Visitors 1968 (Box-folder 1:9)
  Relates to McCoy's appointment to the Board of Vistors at Old Dominion University. These includes news releases on his induction, letters of congratulations from Old Dominion Board of Visitors, President, and Governor, dinner invitation from Alfred B. Rollins, and other letters thanking him for the acceptance of the position. Also one document shows the oath from the office of the Secretary of the Commonwealth.
  Also included in this folder are news articles from the Virginia Pilot and Ledger- Star newspapers. Each article presents information on James L. Bugg, a former president of the Old Dominion University. The articles document his beginning as president and ultimate resignation on behalf of the ODU Board of Visitors.
  Additionally this folder contains news releases related to the Leland Peterson affair. Briefly, this refers to the suspected unfair treatment by some of Dr. Peterson, former president of Old Dominion College. His position was called into question after a story was published in the student magazine "The Gadfly." These articles document the students' protests and concerns as well as those of Dr. Peterson, the hearing of the case by The Old Dominion Board, opinions on the case, and editorials.
- President James L. Bugg, Jr. (Box-folder 1:10)
  Contains articles concerning news of Old Dominion University in general. It provides information on the activities of students at the university, the programs that the college has approved of and will participate in, graduation speakers, and sports.
- Student Protest -- Leland Peterson and the Immaculate Deception (Box-folder 1:11)
- Old Dominion University News -- General 1968 (Box-folder 1:12)